Demand on your CARE: Presentation of illness symptoms in older adults
老唔惱 – 銀齡健康解碼
Process of Healthy Ageing
健康老齡化的過程
From the moment we are born, our journey towards healthy ageing begins.
從我們出生的那一刻起，我們追求健康老齡化的旅程就開始了
It all starts with the genes we inherit from our parents,
一切都源於我們從父母那裡繼承的基因
which play a role in determining how we age.
這些基因會決定我們如何老去
However, it's not just our genes that shape our health as we grow older.
然而，隨著我們年齡增長，塑造我們健康的不僅僅是基因
Our experiences in the womb influenced by and the subsequent environmental exposures
母體子宮內的經歷，以及接下來的環境暴露
and behaviour we are exposed to throughout our lives also have a significant impact.
和行為，也具有顯著的影響
In addition to these factors, we are also born into a social context.
一些通常是不能改變的個人特徵，例如性別和種族
as well as those that can change or are influenced by societal norms,
以及那些可能會改變或受社會規範影響的特徵
such as our occupation, education, gender, or wealth will contribute to our social position in society,
例如職業、教育程度、性別或財富等
which affects the opportunities, barriers we face, as well as our access to resources.
都會影響著我們所遇到的機會、障礙，以及可以獲得的資源
Unfortunately, these interactions can be unfair or inequitable.
不幸的是，這些互動可能是不公平或不平等的
The opportunities and resources we receive may not be based on our needs or rights,
因為我們享有的機會和資源可能不是基於我們的需要或權利
but rather on our social or economic position.
而是基於我們的社會地位或經濟地位
This can lead to disparities in health and well-being among different individuals and communities.
這可能導致不同個體和社群之間在健康和福祉方面存在差異
As we age, our bodies experience natural wear and tear.
隨著年齡增長，我們的身體會自然地經歷磨損
There is a gradual accumulation of molecular and cellular damages,
我們會因為身體細胞逐漸累積的損傷
leading to a general decline in our physiological reserves.
導致生理儲備普遍下降
These physiological and homeostatic changes are largely inevitable,
這些生理和體內平衡的變化很大程度上是不可避免的
although their extent can vary significantly from person to person at any particular chronological age.
儘管這些變化的程度，在任何特定實際年齡的個體之間都會有顯著的差異
Additionally, throughout our lives, we are exposed to a range of positive and negative environmental influences
除此之外，在我們的一生中，我們會接觸一系列好與壞的環境因素
that can further impact our health, such as physiological risk factors
進一步影響我們的健康，例如生理風險因素
(like high blood pressure), diseases, injuries, and broader geriatric syndromes.
（如高血壓）、疾病、受傷和更廣泛的老年症候群
The interaction of these health characteristics will ultimately determine our intrinsic capacity,
這些健康特徵之間的相互作用，最終將決定我們的內在能力
which encompasses all our physical and mental capacities.
其中包括我們所有的生理和心理上的能力
However, whether older people can achieve the things that they value will not be determined just by this capacity
然而，長者能否實現他們所珍視的事物，不僅取決於這種內在能力
but also by further interactions with the environments they inhabit at a particular point in time.
還取決於他們在當刻時間與身處的環境之進一步的互動
On the other hand, our functional ability is a result of the interaction between ourselves and the environment we inhabit.
另一方面，我們的功能能力取決於我們自身和所處環境之間的相互作用
Therefore, healthy ageing is a multidimensional process
因此，健康老齡化是一個多維度的過程
influenced by genetics, lifestyle choices, and social, economic, and environmental factors.
受到遺傳、生活方式選擇以及社會、經濟和環境因素的影響
Since your current state of health is often the outcome of your previous life experiences,
由於現在的健康狀況通常是過去生活經歷的結果
even though we may face many irreversible factors,
即使我們面臨許多無法改變的因素
we can establish healthy lifestyles early on,
但我們可以從現在開始培養健康的生活習慣
such as a healthy diet, regular exercise, and stress management, to counteract the effects of ageing.
例如健康飲食、定期運動和壓力管理，以對抗老齡化的影響
To learn more about it, let’s watch our video
想了解更多，請觀看我們的影片
“10 Tips for Healthy Ageing”.
《健康老齡化之十大秘訣》